<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.0.2//EN//XML" "art502.dtd" [<!ENTITY fx1 SYSTEM "fx1" NDATA IMAGE><!ENTITY fx2 SYSTEM "fx2" NDATA IMAGE>]><article docsubtype="rev"><item-info><jid>PCL</jid><aid>648</aid><ce:pii>S0031-3955(09)00071-6</ce:pii><ce:doi>10.1016/j.pcl.2009.05.017</ce:doi><ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2009">Elsevier Inc.</ce:copyright></item-info><ce:floats><ce:table id="tbl1" frame="topbot" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><ce:label>Table 1</ce:label><ce:caption><ce:simple-para>Landmark adult studies demonstrating clinical antecedents to cardiac arrest</ce:simple-para></ce:caption><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/><thead><row rowsep="1" valign="top"><entry>Publication</entry><entry>Major Findings</entry></row></thead><tbody><row valign="top"><entry>Sax 1987</entry><entry>95% (19 of 20) had acute clinical instability and/or high burden of baseline comorbidities</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry morerows="3">Schein 1990</entry><entry>84% (54 of 64) had new complaints or clinical deterioration within 8&nbsp;hours of arrest</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>70% had abnormal respiratory or neurologic function; 25% had both</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>No consistent laboratory findings were found before arrest</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>77% had underlying diseases not expected to cause death during hospitalization</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry morerows="2">Franklin 1994</entry><entry>66% (99 of 150) had documented clinical deterioration within 6 hours of&nbsp;arrest</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Former ICU patients had significantly higher risk of arrest compared with patients never in the ICU (14.7 versus 6.8&nbsp;per 1000 admissions)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Failures: notifying physician, obtaining/interpreting labs, ICU triage, stabilization on floor</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry morerows="2">Hodgetts 2002</entry><entry>68% (80 of 118) had documented clinical deterioration before arrest</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>100% of patients with potentially avoidable arrests received inadequate pre-arrest treatment</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Avoidable arrests five times more likely for patients on general wards than in ICU</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry morerows="1">Hillman 2002</entry><entry>70% (386 of 551) had serious antecedents within 8 hours of urgent transfer to ICU</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Most commonly: tachycardia, hypotension, tachypnea, sudden change in mental status</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></ce:table><ce:table id="tbl2" frame="topbot" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><ce:label>Table 2</ce:label><ce:caption><ce:simple-para>Clinical outcomes for pediatric rapid response systems</ce:simple-para></ce:caption><tgroup cols="3"><colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/><colspec colnum="3" colname="col3"/><thead><row rowsep="1" valign="top"><entry>Publication</entry><entry>Institution</entry><entry>Statistically Significant Outcomes</entry></row></thead><tbody><row valign="top"><entry>Tibballs 2005</entry><entry>Royal Children&apos;s Hosp. Melbourne, Australia</entry><entry><ce:list><ce:list-item><ce:para>No significant decrease in total cardiac arrest or mortality rates except in those deaths and cardiac arrests the transgressed MET criteria:</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Decrease in mortality 0.11 &rarr; 0 per 1000 admissions</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Decrease in Cardiac Arrests 0.16 &rarr; 0 per 1000 admissions</ce:para></ce:list-item></ce:list></entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Brilli 2007</entry><entry>Cincinnati Children&apos;s Hospital; Cincinnati</entry><entry><ce:list><ce:list-item><ce:para>Decrease in Non-ICU codes 1.54 &rarr; 0.62 per 1000 admissions</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>0.27 &rarr; 0.11 per 1000 patient days</ce:para></ce:list-item></ce:list></entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Sharek 2007</entry><entry>Lucile Packard Children&apos;s Hospital; Stanford University</entry><entry><ce:list><ce:list-item><ce:para>Decrease in non-ICU codes: 2.45 &rarr; 0.69 per 1000 discharges</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>0.52 &rarr; 0.15 per 1000 patient days</ce:para></ce:list-item></ce:list></entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Hunt 2008</entry><entry>Johns Hopkins Hospital Baltimore, Maryland</entry><entry><ce:list><ce:list-item><ce:para>No significant change in cardiopulmonary arrests</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Decrease in respiratory arrest: 1.46 &rarr; 0.40 per 1000 discharges</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>0.23 &rarr; 0.06 per 1000 patient days</ce:para></ce:list-item></ce:list></entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Hanson 2008 (<ce:italic>In press</ce:italic>)</entry><entry>North Carolina Children&apos;s Hospital, Chapel Hill</entry><entry><ce:list><ce:list-item><ce:para>Increase in mean time interval between non-ICU cardiac arrests: 2512 &rarr; 9418 patient days between cardiac arrests</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Decrease in median duration of clinical instability before ICU assessment: 9 h 55 m &rarr; 4 h 15 m</ce:para></ce:list-item></ce:list></entry></row></tbody></tgroup></ce:table><ce:table id="tbl3" frame="topbot" colsep="0" rowsep="0"><ce:label>Table 3</ce:label><ce:caption><ce:simple-para>Assessment and intervention by Pediatric Emergency Response Team at Levine Children&apos;s Hospital (n&nbsp;&equals; 80)</ce:simple-para></ce:caption><tgroup cols="2"><colspec colnum="1" colname="col1"/><colspec colnum="2" colname="col2"/><thead><row rowsep="1" valign="top"><entry>Intervention</entry><entry>Number of Cases (%)</entry></row></thead><tbody><row valign="top"><entry>Airway suctioning</entry><entry>23 (29%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Supplemental oxygen</entry><entry>47 (59%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Bag-valve mask ventilation</entry><entry>15 (19%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Oral/nasal airway</entry><entry>5 (6%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Beta-agonist inhalation</entry><entry>2 (2.5%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Racemic epinephrine inhalation</entry><entry>5 (6%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Chest x-ray</entry><entry>8 (10%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>IV placement</entry><entry>11 (14%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>IV fluid bolus</entry><entry>17 (21%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Naloxone (Narcan)</entry><entry>2 (2.5%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Blood glucose measurement</entry><entry>16 (20%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Dextrose administration (D25 IV)</entry><entry>3 (4%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>Other medications given</entry><entry>17 (21%)</entry></row><row valign="top"><entry>No intervention necessary</entry><entry>6 (7.5%)</entry></row></tbody></tgroup></ce:table><ce:textbox id="tbox1"><ce:label>Box 1</ce:label><ce:caption><ce:simple-para>Pediatric Early Response Team activation criteria at Levine Children&apos;s Hospital</ce:simple-para></ce:caption><ce:textbox-body><ce:sections><ce:para><ce:list><ce:list-item><ce:para>Acute change in HR, BP, RR, O2 Sat</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Acute change in mental status</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Pain or agitation that is difficult to control</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>New or prolonged seizure</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Staff member is worried about a patient</ce:para></ce:list-item></ce:list></ce:para></ce:sections></ce:textbox-body></ce:textbox><ce:textbox id="tbox2"><ce:label>Box 2</ce:label><ce:caption><ce:simple-para>Standing orders for Pediatric Early Response Team at Levine Children&apos;s Hospital</ce:simple-para></ce:caption><ce:textbox-body><ce:sections><ce:para><ce:list><ce:list-item><ce:para>Patient weight: <ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:inline-figure> kg</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Obtain HR, BP, RR, O2 saturation and continue to monitor</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Assess Airway Breathing status</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Assess Circulatory status</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:para>Obtain situation and background information from bedside nurse</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:label><ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:label><ce:para>Oxygen to keep saturations above 92% or for respiratory distress</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:label><ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:label><ce:para>Albuterol 2.5 mg neb (or 2 puffs MDI), repeat &times; 3 doses PRN wheezing/respiratory distress</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:label><ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:label><ce:para>Epinephrine 2.25% (Racemic Epi) 0.5 mL dilutes to 3 mL nebulized &times; 1 dose PRN stridor</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:label><ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:label><ce:para>Obtain blood glucose. If below 40, give D25% 2 mL/kg IV &times; 1 dose.</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:label><ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:label><ce:para>Initiate IV access based on patient condition</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:label><ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:label><ce:para>Normal Saline 20 mL/kg IV &times; 1 dose based on patient condition</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:label><ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:label><ce:para>Narcan 0.1 mg/kg IV for known narcotic administration with altered mental status/resp depression. May repeat &times; 1 dose (max dose 2 mg)</ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:label><ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:label><ce:para>Transfer to PICU based on patient condition; PICU attending notified: Dr. <ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx2"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:para></ce:list-item><ce:list-item><ce:label><ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:label><ce:para>Notify primary attending/service of patient&apos;s condition: Dr. <ce:inline-figure><ce:link locator="fx2"/></ce:inline-figure></ce:para></ce:list-item></ce:list></ce:para></ce:sections></ce:textbox-body></ce:textbox></ce:floats><head><ce:title>Implementing a Pediatric Rapid Response System to&nbsp;Improve Quality and&nbsp;Patient Safety</ce:title><ce:author-group><ce:author id="au1"><ce:given-name>Kerry T.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Van Voorhis</ce:surname><ce:degrees>MD</ce:degrees><ce:cross-ref refid="aff1"><ce:sup>a</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref><ce:cross-ref refid="cor1"><ce:sup>&lowast;</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref><ce:e-address type="email">kerry.vanvoorhis@carolinashealthcare.org</ce:e-address></ce:author><ce:author id="au2"><ce:given-name>Tina Schade</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Willis</ce:surname><ce:degrees>MD</ce:degrees><ce:cross-ref refid="aff2"><ce:sup>b</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref><ce:cross-ref refid="aff3"><ce:sup>c</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref></ce:author><ce:affiliation id="aff1"><ce:label>a</ce:label><ce:textfn>Division of General Pediatrics, Levine Children&apos;s Hospital at Carolinas Medical Center, P.O. Box 32861, Charlotte, NC 28232-2861, USA</ce:textfn></ce:affiliation><ce:affiliation id="aff2"><ce:label>b</ce:label><ce:textfn>Division of Pediatric Critical Care Medicine, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, Suite 20160 Women&apos;s Hospital, 101 Manning Drive, Chapel Hill, NC 27599-7221, USA</ce:textfn></ce:affiliation><ce:affiliation id="aff3"><ce:label>c</ce:label><ce:textfn>North Carolina Children&apos;s Center for Clinical Excellence, NC, USA</ce:textfn></ce:affiliation><ce:correspondence id="cor1"><ce:label>&lowast;</ce:label><ce:text>Corresponding author. Division of General Pediatrics, Levine Children&apos;s Hospital, Carolinas Medical Center, P.O. Box 32861, Charlotte, NC 28232-2861.</ce:text></ce:correspondence></ce:author-group><ce:abstract xml:lang="en"><ce:abstract-sec><ce:simple-para view="extended">Life-threatening events are common in today&apos;s hospitals, where an increasing proportion of patients with urgent admission are cared for by understaffed, often inexperienced personnel. Medical errors play a key role in causing adverse events and failure to rescue deteriorating patients. In-hospital cardiac arrest outcomes are generally poor, but these events are often preceded by a pattern of deterioration with abnormal vital signs and mental status. When hospital staff or family members observe warning signs and trigger timely intervention by a rapid response team, rates of cardiac arrest and mortality can be reduced. Rapid response team involvement can be used to trigger careful review of preceding events to help uncover important systems issues and allow for further improvements in patient safety.</ce:simple-para></ce:abstract-sec></ce:abstract><ce:keywords xml:lang="en"><ce:section-title>Keywords</ce:section-title><ce:keyword><ce:text>Rapid response team</ce:text></ce:keyword><ce:keyword><ce:text>Medical emergency team</ce:text></ce:keyword><ce:keyword><ce:text>Pediatrics</ce:text></ce:keyword><ce:keyword><ce:text>Cardiac arrest</ce:text></ce:keyword><ce:keyword><ce:text>Emergency</ce:text></ce:keyword><ce:keyword><ce:text>Patient safety</ce:text></ce:keyword></ce:keywords></head><body><ce:sections><ce:para>Hospitals today are complex environments serving sicker patients than ever before. Patients who are not acutely ill are often managed as outpatients, leaving inpatient units to care for those with more severe conditions. According to the World Health Organization, the proportion of emergency admissions continues to rise in most countries,<ce:cross-ref refid="bib1"><ce:sup>1</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> while pressures to contain health care costs have resulted in shorter inpatient length of stay.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib2"><ce:sup>2</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> At the same time, recruiting and retaining trained nurses is increasingly difficult,<ce:cross-ref refid="bib3"><ce:sup>3</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> and physician work hours are trending downward.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib4"><ce:sup>4</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> The result is a more intricate inpatient milieu with proportionally fewer staff equipped to care for sicker patients who are more likely to experience life-threatening events, including cardiopulmonary arrest and unplanned admission to the intensive care unit (ICU).</ce:para><ce:para>Life-threatening events frequently arise in the hospital setting. Recent estimates suggest that 370,000 to 750,000 in-hospital resuscitation attempts are made every year in the United States.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib5"><ce:sup>5</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> The incidence of adult in-hospital cardiac arrest ranges from 1 to 5 events per 1000 hospital admissions,<ce:cross-ref refid="bib5"><ce:sup>5</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> while the incidence in children&apos;s hospitals is significantly lower at 0.19 to 2.45 events per 1000 admissions.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib6"><ce:sup>6</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> These events often result from preventable medical errors. Given the dismal survival rate of in-hospital cardiac arrest, it is critical to develop systems that recognize predictable clinical warning signs and intervene before patients reach the point of arrest.</ce:para><ce:section id="sec2"><ce:section-title>Medical error and adverse events</ce:section-title><ce:para>A problem closely linked to the rising complexity of hospitals, and a factor in a significant proportion of life-threatening events, is medical error. In its 2000 report, <ce:italic>To Err is Human</ce:italic>, The Institute of Medicine concluded that between 44,000 and 98,000 patients die each year in US hospitals as a result of preventable clinical errors.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib7"><ce:sup>7</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> There are many terms used to describe inappropriate care and adverse outcomes experienced by patients. A list compiled by Andrews and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib8"><ce:sup>8</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> includes &ldquo;adverse or untoward events, maloccurrences, complications, medical injuries, therapeutic misadventures, substandard care, unexpected outcomes, preventable deaths, iatrogenic injuries, mishaps, errors, negligence, and malpractice.&rdquo; Resar and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib9"><ce:sup>9</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> have defined medical error as &ldquo;the failure of a planned action to be completed as intended or the use of a wrong plan to achieve an aim.&rdquo;</ce:para><ce:para>Estimates of the incidence of harm caused by medical error vary widely, depending on the research methodology and population studied. The Harvard Medical Practice Study, a retrospective chart review published in 1990, showed that 3.7% of more than 30,000 patient records from New York hospitals revealed an incident that two physicians agreed was adverse and caused serious harm.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib10"><ce:sup>10</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> Investigators in this study defined adverse events according to a legal-policy model, as their goal in measuring the event rate was to determine the feasibility of a no-fault system of compensation for medical malpractice.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib8"><ce:sup>8</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> Given the nature of the study, the authors only included errors that were clearly documented in the medical record. However, evidence from other studies suggests that fewer than 10% of adverse events are revealed in the medical record because documentation by hospital staff is often voluntary, time intensive, and perceived as potentially punitive.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib11"><ce:sup>11</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref></ce:para><ce:para>Other studies have demonstrated much higher rates of harm from medical error. For example, Steel and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib12"><ce:sup>12</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> found that an alarming 36% of 815 consecutive patients admitted to a general medical service at a university hospital had an iatrogenic illness, and 9% had an iatrogenic event that was life threatening or resulted in subsequent disability. This 1981 study reached the following conclusion: &ldquo;Given the increasing number and complexity of diagnostic procedures and therapeutic agents, monitoring of untoward events is essential, and attention should be paid to educational efforts to reduce the risks of iatrogenic illness.&rdquo;</ce:para><ce:para>Rather than relying on medical records alone, Andrews and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib8"><ce:sup>8</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> searched for medical errors associated with 1047 adult surgical patients during inpatient rounds and case conferences. They reported that adverse events as a result of medical error occurred in 480 (46%) of the patients. Eighteen percent of patients experienced serious injury caused by medical error, with outcomes ranging from temporary physical disability to death. Patients who experienced adverse events stayed longer in the hospital (24 days versus 9 days for those without medical errors), and longer stays were associated with more medical errors. Adverse events were more likely to occur in patients with severe illness. Fifty-five percent of patients who required ICU care during their hospital stay experienced harm from medical error, compared with 38% of patients who did not spend time in the ICU.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib8"><ce:sup>8</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref></ce:para><ce:para>One or more causes of error were identified for just over half of the adverse events. Errors by an individual, such as poor technical performance, poor judgment, or failure to obtain or act on information contributed to 38% of the adverse events. Flawed interactions between individuals, such as failure of a consultant team to communicate adequately with the requesting team, were found to be responsible for 16% of the errors. About 10% of the errors were related generally to administrative decisions or protocols, such as inadequate staffing or defective equipment.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib8"><ce:sup>8</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref></ce:para><ce:para>Compared with adults, published estimates of adverse events in pediatric patients are few. Three studies using the &ldquo;first-generation&rdquo; methodology of the Harvard Medical Practice Study (nontargeted retrospective chart review) revealed similar low rates of adverse events in pediatric inpatients (2.3%, 2.9%, and 3.7%).<ce:cross-ref refid="bib11"><ce:sup>11</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> Studies using trigger tools, methods for increasing the efficiency of detection, have revealed higher rates of error. For example, in a 12-site children&apos;s hospital quality and safety collaborative study, Takata and Currier<ce:cross-ref refid="bib13"><ce:sup>13</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> reported a rate of 11.1 adverse drug events per 100 pediatric inpatients. Twenty-two percent of these errors were deemed preventable.</ce:para><ce:para>While post hoc analysis often links adverse events in the medical setting to &ldquo;human error,&rdquo; many can be traced to a systems problem, defined by Bright and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib2"><ce:sup>2</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> as a sequence of events in the macro- and micro-environment that involve deficiencies in the structure and organization of health care. Cook and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib14"><ce:sup>14</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> point out that gaps in the continuity of care, such as the loss of information that occur at change of shift and transfer to a different facility, makes it more difficult to appreciate trends in a deteriorating patient&apos;s condition. Resolving systems problems and eliminating preventable medical errors is an important means of reducing adverse events, including cardiac arrest.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec3"><ce:section-title>Outcomes for cardiac arrest</ce:section-title><ce:para>Research over the past several decades has led to improved understanding of the epidemiology and pathophysiology of cardiac arrest in both adults and children. Corresponding advances in resuscitation, particularly coordinated strategies to strengthen the community chain of survival, have resulted in a marked improvement in outcomes for arrests that occur outside of the hospital setting.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib15"><ce:sup>15</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> Efforts by the American Heart Association and other groups have brought these advances to the&nbsp;public in effective ways. As a result, an increasing segment of the general public is equipped to react quickly to an unresponsive person outside the hospital setting. Peberdy and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib15"><ce:sup>15</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> point out that today one can find automated external defibrillators in schools, theaters, grocery stores, restaurants, shopping malls, airports, and many other public places. In addition to police and firefighters, many security officers, airline flight attendants, and trained laypersons are trained to use them while waiting for paramedics to arrive. In an effort to make the technical aspects of resuscitation easier to remember, elements of popular culture have been incorporated into education. The 1970s song &ldquo;Staying Alive&rdquo; by the Bee Gees is now immortalized as the proper tempo for chest compressions (100/minute). &ldquo;Another One Bites the Dust&rdquo; by Queen is a less hopeful but acceptable alternative. As a result of these developments, resuscitation in the prehospital setting is gradually moving closer to that in the hospital setting.</ce:para><ce:para>In contrast, procedures and outcomes for in-hospital resuscitation have remained relatively unchanged over the past 30 years.<ce:cross-refs refid="bib5 bib16"><ce:sup>5,16</ce:sup></ce:cross-refs> In most hospitals, a &ldquo;code team&rdquo; responds to cardiac arrest in a general ward area. However, this approach has not been associated with a significant improvement in the mortality rate.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib17"><ce:sup>17</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> According to prospective data from 14,720 in-hospital cardiac arrests recorded by National Registry of Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation (NRCPR), fewer than half (44%) of adult in-hospital arrest victims had return of spontaneous circulation, and only 17% survived to hospital discharge. Pediatric patients (&lt;18 years of age) in the study had a higher survival rate of 27%. Thirty-four percent of pediatric survivors had a poor neurologic function postarrest.<ce:cross-refs refid="bib15 bib18"><ce:sup>15,18</ce:sup></ce:cross-refs> A 1999 meta-analysis of 554 in-hospital pediatric cardiac arrests demonstrated a similar survival rate of 24%. Twenty-two percent of survivors had poor neurologic function postarrest.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib19"><ce:sup>19</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref></ce:para><ce:para>For both children and adults in the NRCPR study, survival rates were higher when arrests occurred in monitored units and when the resuscitation team arrived quickly. Ninety-five percent of the pediatric arrests in the NRCPR study were either monitored or directly witnessed by a member of the health care team at the time of the event. In 86% of the 207 hospitals submitting data for the study, an organized emergency team responds 24 hours per day.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib15"><ce:sup>15</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref></ce:para><ce:para>Berg and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib20"><ce:sup>20</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> carefully analyzed the 880 pediatric arrests reported in the NRCPR study. Pediatric cardiac arrests occurred in the intensive care unit (ICU; 65%), emergency department (ED; 13%), general pediatric ward (14%), operating room (OR) or postanesthesia care unit (3%), diagnostic area (2%), and other/unknown location (2%). Immediate causes of pediatric cardiac arrests included acute respiratory insufficiency (57%), hypotension (61%), arrhythmia (49%), metabolic/electrolyte disturbance (12%), airway obstruction (5%), and acute pulmonary edema (4%). Many patients had more than one immediate cause.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec4"><ce:section-title>Warning signs and symptoms</ce:section-title><ce:para>Observations over the past two decades have changed the belief that most incidents of cardiopulmonary arrest are sudden and unpredictable. In fact, cardiopulmonary arrest is often preceded by up to several hours of warning signs and symptoms that predict subsequent deterioration. This pattern has been demonstrated repeatedly and reliably in a series of prospective studies of adult patients who experience cardiac arrest on a general inpatient ward. In each of the studies listed in <ce:cross-ref refid="tbl1">Table 1</ce:cross-ref><ce:float-anchor refid="tbl1"/>, patients who arrested in other locations (ED, OR, ICU) and those who had &ldquo;do not resuscitate&rdquo; (DNR) orders were excluded. Each study builds on the findings of its predecessors, resulting in a clear pattern of events that typically precede in-hospital cardiac arrest.</ce:para><ce:para>Franklin and Mathew<ce:cross-ref refid="bib21"><ce:sup>21</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> investigated nurse and physician responses to the pre-arrest decline of 150 adult inpatients. In 99 (66%) of 150 patients, a nurse or physician documented deterioration in the patient&apos;s condition within 6 hours of arrest. Of the 51 arrests that could not be anticipated, 2 were in-hospital suicides and 4 occurred in association with medical procedures. Several pitfalls were appreciated in the 99 potentially predictable arrests. In 25 cases, a nurse documented deterioration but failed to notify a physician. In 42 cases, the ward physician was notified but failed to alert the ICU physician. With another group of patients, the ward physician failed to obtain (30 cases) or respond to an abnormal arterial blood gas (8 cases) in the setting of respiratory distress and/or altered mental status. ICU triage error was noted in 32 cases, most of which involved failure of the ICU physician to stabilize the patient before transfer to the ICU. The authors concluded that strategies to prevent cardiac arrest should include training for nurses and physicians that concentrates on cardiopulmonary stabilization and how to respond to neurologic and respiratory deterioration.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib21"><ce:sup>21</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref></ce:para><ce:para>Hodgetts and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib22"><ce:sup>22</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> reviewed records from 32,348 consecutive adult admissions over a 1-year period and found 118 in-hospital cardiac arrests that prompted code team involvement. An expert panel reviewed each case and unanimously agreed that 68% of in-hospital arrests were potentially avoidable. Cardiac arrests were more likely to occur on weekends than weekdays. The odds of potentially avoidable cardiac arrest were five times greater for patients on general wards than critical care areas, and patients who arrested in critical care areas were more likely to survive. The odds of a potentially avoidable cardiac arrest was 12.6 times greater for patients in a clinical area judged &ldquo;inappropriate&rdquo; for their main complaint, compared with those in &ldquo;appropriate&rdquo; areas. The panel agreed that 100% of potentially avoidable arrests were judged to have received inadequate treatment before arrest. The authors noted several common errors including delays and errors in diagnosis, inadequate interpretation of test results, incomplete treatment, inexperienced physicians, and management in inappropriate clinical areas.</ce:para><ce:para>Hillman and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib23"><ce:sup>23</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> studied the characteristics and incidence of serious abnormalities in 551 adult patients before unplanned ICU admission. They found that patients transferred urgently to ICU from the general ward were more severely ill, had longer ICU stays, and higher mortality (47.6% mortality) than those admitted from the ED (31.5%) and OR (19%). Seventy percent of ward patients had serious documented antecedents during the 8 hours before transfer, most commonly including hypotension, tachycardia, tachypnea, and/or sudden change in level of consciousness.</ce:para><ce:para>A prospective study of 6300 hospitalized adults by Buist et&nbsp;al.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib17"><ce:sup>17</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> further clarified a set of abnormal antecedent clinical parameters with a high predictive value for subsequent cardiac arrest. These included a decrease in Glasgow Coma Score by two points, onset of coma, hypotension (&lt;90 mm Hg), respiratory rate less than 6/minute, hypoxia (oxygen saturation &lt;90%, on or off oxygen therapy), and bradycardia higher than 30/minute. The presence of any of these six factors was associated with a 6.8-fold increase in the risk of in-hospital mortality. Risk of mortality was higher for patients with multiple abnormalities (88% risk with four) compared with a single factor (16% risk). The authors recommended that these criteria be used for activating a rescue response before further deterioration.</ce:para><ce:para>These and other studies<ce:cross-refs refid="bib24 bib25"><ce:sup>24,25</ce:sup></ce:cross-refs> clearly demonstrate that most adult patients who suffer cardiac arrest on the general inpatient floor exhibit antecedent abnormal signs and symptoms. Prospective studies documenting the reliable presence of similar patterns in children are lacking. While some hospitalized children may suffer sudden and unexpected cardiac arrests from acute arrhythmia, airway obstruction, seizure, or other events, the more common pattern is thought to be a gradual progression of hypoxemia and hemodynamic instability.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib6"><ce:sup>6</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> &ldquo;Vital signs&rdquo; have earned that distinction for good reason.</ce:para><ce:para>The limitation of these studies, and resulting challenge for hospital personnel, is the absence of a reliable denominator (ie, how many patients exhibiting abnormal signs and symptoms did <ce:italic>not</ce:italic> suffer cardiac arrest). No doubt, the denominator is very large. For example, Buist and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib17"><ce:sup>17</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> found that serious clinical abnormalities resolved spontaneously in 67% of patients. However, given universally poor outcomes for in-hospital cardiac arrest, the need to respond urgently to patients with serious abnormalities is compelling, prompting the Institute for Healthcare Improvement and others to call for the implementation of rapid response systems to recognize and respond to deteriorating hospitalized patients of all ages to prevent cardiac arrest.</ce:para><ce:para>There are multiple single institution studies in adult populations showing statistically significant decreases in cardiac arrest and mortality rates after the development of a rapid response system.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib26"><ce:sup>26</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> However, the only multicenter cluster randomized control study examining the effects of a rapid response system on cardiac arrests and mortality in adult populations showed no significant differences between groups, although both control and intervention institutions experienced significant improvements in cardiac arrest rates at the end of the study period.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib27"><ce:sup>27</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> There are few published studies examining rapid response systems in single pediatric institutions and no multicenter studies in a pediatric population. Despite the paucity of published studies, several pediatric studies report significant decreases in cardiac and/or respiratory arrest rates<ce:cross-refs refid="bib28 bib29 bib30 bib31 bib32"><ce:sup>28&ndash;32</ce:sup></ce:cross-refs> and one study reports a significant decrease in hospital-wide mortality rates.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib31"><ce:sup>31</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref></ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec5"><ce:section-title>Outcome measures of pediatric rapid response systems</ce:section-title><ce:para>As rapid response systems are implemented and sustained with specific outcomes in mind, process and outcome measures must be followed to detect changes at the institution level as well as provide a framework for benchmarking. In 2007, the International Liaison Committee on Resuscitation (ILCOR) published &ldquo;recommended guidelines for monitoring, reporting, and conducting research on medical emergency team, outreach, and rapid response systems: an Utstein-style scientific statement.&rdquo;<ce:cross-ref refid="bib33"><ce:sup>33</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> In&nbsp;addition to patient and hospital demographics, peri-event data, and universal nomenclature, there are specific recommendations for patient and hospital outcomes data reporting. According to their recommendations, hospital outcomes should include total acute care discharges whether alive or dead, hospital deaths, DNR deaths, number of emergency team activations, total number of in-hospital cardiac arrests, and cardiac arrests occurring in non-ICU, operating room, or emergency departments.</ce:para><ce:para>Although most of the adult literature has used similar outcomes in published studies, there remain many differences in the definitions of reported outcomes in published studies of pediatric rapid response systems (<ce:cross-ref refid="tbl2">Table 2</ce:cross-ref><ce:float-anchor refid="tbl2"/>). These differences make it difficult to assess and compare the small number of pediatric rapid response system studies in the literature. For example, Tibballs and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib28"><ce:sup>28</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> and Hanson and colleagues,<ce:cross-ref refid="bib32"><ce:sup>32</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> like in adult studies, report cardiac arrests as one of their main outcome variables. Brilli and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib29"><ce:sup>29</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> and Sharek and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib31"><ce:sup>31</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> use the term &ldquo;code&rdquo; to include respiratory and cardiac arrests and Hunt and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib30"><ce:sup>30</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> report both &ldquo;cardiopulmonary&rdquo; and &ldquo;respiratory&rdquo; arrests. In addition, these outcomes are indexed differently in pediatric studies with many reporting arrest events per 1000 patient days instead of or in addition to 1000 admissions/discharges. Although patient days likely offer a more accurate measure of effect on the patient population, it is not standardized for reporting in the literature. Effects on wards mortality before and after rapid response system development were reported by Brilli and colleagues,<ce:cross-ref refid="bib29"><ce:sup>29</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> Hunt and colleagues,<ce:cross-ref refid="bib30"><ce:sup>30</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> and Tibballs and colleagues,<ce:cross-ref refid="bib28"><ce:sup>28</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> whereas Sharek and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib31"><ce:sup>31</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> and Hanson and colleagues<ce:cross-ref refid="bib32"><ce:sup>32</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> focused on hospital-wide mortality rates. It is clear that pediatric institutions need further recommendations for standardized measures of rapid response systems. One immediate solution would be to follow the ILCOR recommendations for data reporting for all rapid response systems including those in pediatric populations.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec6"><ce:section-title>Implementation of a successful rapid response system</ce:section-title><ce:para>According to the Medical Emergency Team Consensus Conference, successful rapid response systems include four necessary components: (1) an afferent limb, (2) an efferent limb, (3) an evaluative/process improvement limb, and (4) an administrative limb.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib34"><ce:sup>34</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> The afferent limb is defined as the component of the emergency response system that is able to detect an event and trigger a response. The efferent limb provides a crisis response including resources such as a medical emergency team (MET) or rapid response team (RRT) and equipment. The evaluative/process improvement component exists to improve patient care and safety. Finally, the administrative limb exists to implement and sustain the service. To highlight the process of developing a pediatric rapid response system and measuring its effects on patient safety, we share case examples that describe our experiences at the North Carolina Children&apos;s Hospital at the University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill and Levine Children&apos;s Hospital in Charlotte, North Carolina.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec7"><ce:section-title>Case example: University of North Carolina-Chapel Hill</ce:section-title><ce:para>An institution-wide pediatric rapid response system (PRRS) has been active at North Carolina Children&apos;s Hospital since August 2005. Antecedents described in the adult literature along with pattern antecedents identified in detailed institution-specific chart reviews were used to establish the criteria for activation of the RRT. Calling criteria were designed without numeric vital sign parameters to be highly sensitive for pre&ndash;cardiac arrest states. The criteria for activation are displayed in poster format throughout the hospital. The PRRS includes all four consensus conference components.</ce:para><ce:para>The afferent limb relies on human assessment and interpretation of monitoring to detect an event and activate the RRT. The primary system change is the empowerment of any member of the hospital staff or family member to activate the RRT. The RRT is activated though both a pager call to team members and a public announcement. A public announcement is used not only to notify the RRT members but also the&nbsp;primary team to assist in the decision-making process and foster acceptance of the team to other hospital staff.</ce:para><ce:para>The efferent limb, or RRT, includes a pediatric critical care fellow or attending, a senior resident, a critical care charge nurse, and a pediatric respiratory therapist. The primary team for the patient is also expected to be present and participate as members of the RRT. The RRT has all of the following competencies: (1) ability to prescribe therapy; (2) advanced airway management; (3) capability to establish central venous access; and (4) ability to begin ICU level of care at the bedside.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib34"><ce:sup>34</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> The team responds to all areas excluding the neonatal and pediatric intensive care units. This includes clinics within the hospital building, adult patient areas where pediatric visitors may be present, inpatient wards, burn unit, bone marrow transplant unit, radiology, or any other physical space within the institution walls.</ce:para><ce:para>On arrival to the patient&apos;s bedside, the RRT provides immediate medical evaluation and treatment as required. The team then communicates further treatment plans to the patient&apos;s primary medical team and family. The team is trained to perform a debriefing with immediate feedback to the resident physicians and nurses regarding recognition of clinical deterioration and strategies for improvement. The RRT members are instructed to adopt a supportive attitude and not to make negative comments. An RRT activation form is completed by the pediatric critical care physician and then collected for performance improvement.</ce:para><ce:para>The administrative and process improvement limbs are necessary for implementing and sustaining the system. Before implementation, a 4-month period of educational sessions for all medical staff including physicians, nurses, respiratory therapists, chaplains, security, and communications staff was completed. During these sessions, criteria for activation of the RRT were reviewed, illustrative cases discussed, and concerns and questions addressed.</ce:para><ce:para>Once education was complete, the system changes were initiated without a run-in period. From that time onward the rapid response system has been evaluated by prospectively collected data recorded on RRT activation forms and existing performance improvement database information. The administrative committee meets monthly to review the data collected and discuss individual cases that prompted additional safety concerns. Further root cause analyses are performed as needed to address these safety concerns. As a result, several changes to the system have been made to further decrease variation in response and improve safety. For example, a new policy preventing the cancellation of a &ldquo;code blue&rdquo; or RRT call was implemented to reinforce the concept that there are no false alarms. In addition, the pediatric ICU staff began activating the RRT for urgent consults when it was identified that the team was not being used fully. Individual cases are discussed formally at a monthly resident conference to reinforce management and resuscitation of the critically ill pediatric patient.</ce:para><ce:para>As a result of the PRRS, the mean time interval between cardiac arrests increased significantly from a baseline of 2512 to 9418 days, indicating a significant decrease in non-ICU cardiac arrests. In addition, median duration of predefined clinical instability before assessment by ICU personnel decreased from 9 hours 55 minutes to 4 hours 15 minutes postintervention (<ce:italic>P</ce:italic> &equals; .028).<ce:cross-ref refid="bib32"><ce:sup>32</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> The duration of clinical instability significantly decreased for unplanned ICU admissions whether assessed by the RRT or not, indicating that implementation of a PRRS resulted in a hospital-wide culture change favoring early assessment by critical care personnel. This culture change is likely the most important aspect of rapid response systems leading to early recognition and treatment of clinical deterioration. One recent study similarly found that DNR orders and delayed MET activation are the strongest independent predictors of mortality in patients receiving a Medical Emergency Team review. The investigators stressed that avoidance of delayed MET activation should be a priority for hospitals operating rapid response systems.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib35"><ce:sup>35</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref></ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec8"><ce:section-title>Case example: Levine Children&apos;s Hospital</ce:section-title><ce:para>An institution-wide Pediatric Early Response Team (PERT) was initiated at Levine Children&apos;s Hospital (LCH) in 2004, and has evolved considerably since then. The initial afferent system for identifying a deteriorating patient used evidence-based criteria for airway, breathing, circulatory, and neurologic concerns, but activating the efferent response was inefficient and cumbersome. The nurse typically paged the inpatient physician and charge nurse and waited for recommendations or &ldquo;permission&rdquo; to have the ICU team evaluate the patient. In spring 2007, a multidisciplinary task force including representatives from critical care, inpatient general pediatrics, nursing, respiratory care, and risk management began a collaboration to enhance the system by adopting the latest evidence-based strategies. LCH adopted the simple age-neutral activation criteria listed in <ce:cross-ref refid="tbox1">Box 1</ce:cross-ref><ce:float-anchor refid="tbox1"/>.</ce:para><ce:para>The revised system empowers concerned staff members to activate PERT by calling the hospital paging operator. A group text page immediately informs PERT members, including a pediatric hospitalist, supervising resident physician, critical care charge nurse, and pediatric respiratory therapist. Each PERT member has authority to implement a wide range of standing orders shown in <ce:cross-ref refid="tbox2">Box 2</ce:cross-ref><ce:float-anchor refid="tbox2"/>, including transfer to a higher level of care. After the patient has been stabilized, a brief record is completed to document which staff member initiated the call, reason for the call, assessment and intervention measures, and outcomes. In addition, the patient&apos;s bedside nurse completes a feedback tool to record response time; quality of communication between the PERT members, primary inpatient team, nursing staff, and patient/family; and suggestions for improvement. Staff members initiate PERT are acknowledged for their commitment to patient safety by a personalized letter from the chief nursing officer and chief medical officer. There are no &ldquo;false alarms.&rdquo;</ce:para><ce:para>PERT calls at LCH increased significantly since implementation of the direct activation mechanism in May 2007. The average number of PERT events per 1000 discharges was 1.37 during the 12 months before implementation, compared with 8.42 during the 18 months after implementation. There were 80 PERT events between July 1, 2006, and December 31, 2008. PERT was predominantly activated by the patient&apos;s bedside nurse (84%), and occasionally by the physician (9%), charge nurse (5%), or respiratory therapist (2.5%). Activation triggers included acute changes in heart rate (22%), blood pressure (7.5%), respiratory rate (41%), hypoxia (35%), mental status (25%), and other/staff concern (68%). More than one reason for calling PERT was frequently documented. PERT arrival occurred within 5 minutes of the call in 95% of cases, and within 10 minutes in all remaining cases. Assessments and interventions provided by PERT are documented in <ce:cross-ref refid="tbl3">Table 3</ce:cross-ref><ce:float-anchor refid="tbl3"/>.</ce:para><ce:para>PERT intervention was typically brief, lasting less than 30 minutes in 86% (69/80) of cases. Nine cases lasted 30 to 60 minutes, and two cases lasted 60 to 90 minutes. Education to initiate ICU transfer for interventions lasting more than 30 minutes was subsequently provided. Following PERT intervention, 56% (45/80) of patients remained on the general or progressive floor, whereas 39% (31/80) were transferred to the ICU, including three cases where the patient required resuscitation for cardiac arrest on the general ward. Four patients requiring PERT intervention were admitted to the hospital from an outpatient area such as radiology or dialysis following the event.</ce:para><ce:para>Levine Children&apos;s Hospital opened in December 2007, 6 months after implementation of the revised PERT system. Despite a 10% increase in inpatient volume in 2008 compared with 2007, the mean rate of non-ICU codes (defined at LCH as either cardiac or respiratory arrest) decreased to 1.5 per 1000 discharges. The rate of codes outside the ICU had previously been approximately four cases per 1000 discharges. Interestingly, there were zero non-ICU codes during the period of intense education about upcoming changes to PERT. Since the PERT revision, the rate of non-ICU codes has remained below 2.25 per 1000 discharges, even during periods when total pediatric codes (ICU &plus; non-ICU) exceeded 10 per 1000 discharges.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec9"><ce:section-title>Implementation of family activation</ce:section-title><ce:para>At Levine Children&apos;s Hospital, family members are encouraged to immediately notify a staff member when they are concerned about their child. The NC Children&apos;s Hospital used a similar approach initially. During the first year after implementation of the PRRS at NC Children&apos;s Hospital, &ldquo;family concern&rdquo; was one of the reasons for activation in 8% of the calls. More than half of those patients required transfer to the ICU, demonstrating that the calls were appropriate and necessary. In the spring of 2007, after piloting the system in two units, family activation was introduced throughout the institution, allowing families to directly activate the RRT using the same system as the hospital staff without a triage step.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib36"><ce:sup>36</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> Researchers at the University of Pittsburgh Medical Center recently described their patient and family activation system. At their institution, a call by a family member results in the activation of a special Condition HELP team (a physician, a nursing supervisor, and a patient advocate) who evaluates whether to elevate the situation and activate a rapid response emergency team, called Condition A (cardiopulmonary arrest) or Condition C (a crisis that might result in imminent arrest).<ce:cross-ref refid="bib37"><ce:sup>37</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref></ce:para><ce:para>The 2009 National Patient Safety Goals have identified partnership with patients and families as &ldquo;an important characteristic of a culture of safety&rdquo; and according to the Institute for Family-Centered Care, the core concepts of patient- and family-centered care are dignity and respect, information sharing, participation, and collaboration.<ce:cross-refs refid="bib38 bib39"><ce:sup>38,39</ce:sup></ce:cross-refs> These goals are even more important in pediatrics, where patients are reliant on parents and caregivers for most of their needs.</ce:para><ce:para>At NC Children&apos;s Hospital, members of the medical staff feared that family activation would result in numerous calls for nonemergent situations as well as calls that would be better routed to patient relations representatives. Focus groups, open communication, and finally a pilot of family activation on two units of the institution reassured the medical staff and families that the introduction of family activation would not disrupt or overwhelm the existing rapid response system. The rule of &ldquo;no false alarms&rdquo; helps all staff understand that any serious concern of a family member or a member of the child&apos;s medical team is valid cause for activating the system.</ce:para><ce:para>At the time of admission, all patients and families are educated about the RRT by their nurse. If families are not educated at the time of admission, several educational tools are available to ensure that families are fully equipped to activate the RRT. The key elements of the family activation and education include staff education and mock scripts, bilingual flyers in visitor areas and waiting rooms, electronic chart education reminders for nurses, and large colorful bilingual posters in each patient room. The posters serve as a both a reminder of the number to call and a prompt for nurses to provide education at the time of admission. A tear-off card mechanism for activation by non&ndash;English-speaking families is available next to the poster in every room.</ce:para><ce:para>Audits and interviews with families to assess their understanding of the RRT in their own words are conducted routinely, with feedback provided to the unit staff. Through audits, it has been discovered that the poster alone is not sufficient education for families. In fact, many families have never read the information unless their nurse mentioned it at the time of admission. Without the poster, however, it may be difficult to remember the phone number to call to activate the team. In addition to the other tools, information about the RRT is included in the hospital guide that is provided to families at the time of admission.</ce:para><ce:para>Since the introduction of family activation, the mean number of RRT calls has increased significantly from 16 to 24 calls per 1000 discharges (Willis, unpublished data, 2009). The number of rapid response calls made directly by a family member is very low&mdash;only two calls during the first year of implementation. Many staff members have indicated that families prefer to have a medical professional call on their behalf. Despite this fact, family concern continues to be recorded as a reason for activation in 6% of all calls. Efforts to provide education to patients and families about rapid response systems serve not only to help them summon care in a time of need, but also to move toward a hospital-wide culture of recognizing families as critical members of the medical team.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec10"><ce:section-title>Use of rapid response system for quality improvement</ce:section-title><ce:para>There are many reported benefits of rapid response systems beyond a reduction in cardiac arrest and mortality rates. These include improved staff satisfaction and safety culture, improved nursing documentation, earlier palliative care, and improved education for physician trainees.<ce:cross-refs refid="bib26 bib40 bib41 bib42 bib43"><ce:sup>26,40&ndash;43</ce:sup></ce:cross-refs> In addition, rapid response and medical emergency team activations can be used for detection of medical errors and system safety issues. In fact, at one institution, more than 30% of RRT activation reviews detected a medical error, and a focus on standardization of hospital processes was completed to improve hospital-wide safety.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib44"><ce:sup>44</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> These processes included standardized protocols for hypoglycemia and transfer of patients. Standardized protocols can also be used by RRTs to improve care of sepsis patients.<ce:cross-ref refid="bib45"><ce:sup>45</ce:sup></ce:cross-ref> RRT activations can easily be incorporated into existing morbidity and mortality reviews and used as a trigger tool for system reviews and further improvement in hospital processes.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec11"><ce:section-title>Summary</ce:section-title><ce:para>Life-threatening events are common in today&apos;s complex hospital environment, where an increasing proportion of patients with urgent admission for severe illness are cared for by understaffed, often inexperienced personnel. Medical errors play a key role in causing adverse events and failure to rescue deteriorating patients. Outcomes for in-hospital cardiac arrest in both adults and children are generally poor, but these events are often preceded by a pattern of deterioration with abnormal vital signs and mental status. Fortunately, when hospital staff or a family member observes warning signs and triggers timely intervention by a rapid response team, rates of cardiac arrest and mortality can be reduced. Moreover, rapid response team involvement can be used to trigger careful review of preceding events to help uncover important systems issues and allow for further improvements in patient safety.</ce:para></ce:section></ce:sections></body><tail><ce:bibliography><ce:section-title>References</ce:section-title><ce:bibliography-sec><ce:bib-reference id="bib1"><ce:label>1</ce:label><ce:other-ref><ce:textref>World Health Organization report: emergency medical services. 2008.</ce:textref></ce:other-ref></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib2"><ce:label>2</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>D.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Bright</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>W.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Walker</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Bion</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Clinical review: outreach&mdash;a strategy for improving the care of the acutely ill hospitalized patient</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Crit Care</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>8</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>1</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2004</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>33</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>40</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib3"><ce:label>3</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Buchan</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Global nursing shortages</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>BMJ</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>324</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>7340</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2002</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>751</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>752</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib4"><ce:label>4</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>I.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Philibert</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>P.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Friedmann</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>W.T.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Williams</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>New requirements for resident duty hours</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>JAMA</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>288</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>9</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2002</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>1112</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>1114</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib5"><ce:label>5</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>C.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Sandroni</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Nolan</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>F.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Cavallaro</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>In-hospital cardiac arrest: incidence, prognosis and possible measures to improve survival</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Intensive Care Med</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>33</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>2</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2007</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>237</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>245</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib6"><ce:label>6</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Tibballs</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>E.W.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>van der Jagt</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Medical emergency and rapid response teams</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Pediatr Clin North Am</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>55</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>4</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2008</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>989</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>1010</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib7"><ce:label>7</ce:label><ce:other-ref><ce:textref>Kohn LT, Corrigan JM, Donaldson MS. To err is human: building a safer health system. 1999.</ce:textref></ce:other-ref></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib8"><ce:label>8</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>L.B.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Andrews</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>C.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Stocking</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>T.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Krizek</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>An alternative strategy for studying adverse events in medical care</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Lancet</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>349</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>9048</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>1997</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>309</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>313</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib9"><ce:label>9</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>R.K.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Resar</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.D.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Rozich</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>D.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Classen</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Methodology and rationale for the measurement of harm with trigger tools</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Qual Saf Health Care</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>12</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>Suppl 2</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2003</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>ii39</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>ii45</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib10"><ce:label>10</ce:label><ce:other-ref><ce:textref>Harvard Medical Practice Study. Patients, doctors and lawyers and medical injury, malpractice litigation, and patient compensation in New York. 1990.</ce:textref></ce:other-ref></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib11"><ce:label>11</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>P.J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Sharek</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>D.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Classen</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>The incidence of adverse events and medical error in pediatrics</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Pediatr Clin North Am</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>53</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>6</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2006</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>1067</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>1077</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib12"><ce:label>12</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>K.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Steel</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>P.M.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Gertman</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>C.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Crescenzi</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Iatrogenic illness on a general medical service at a university hospital</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>N Engl J Med</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>304</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>11</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>1981</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>638</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>642</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib13"><ce:label>13</ce:label><ce:other-ref><ce:textref>Takata G, Currier K. Enhancing patient safety through improved detection of adverse drug events.</ce:textref></ce:other-ref></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib14"><ce:label>14</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>R.I.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Cook</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Render</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>D.D.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Woods</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Gaps in the continuity of care and progress on patient safety</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>BMJ</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>320</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>7237</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2000</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>791</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>794</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib15"><ce:label>15</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.A.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Peberdy</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>W.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Kaye</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.P.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Ornato</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Cardiopulmonary resuscitation of adults in the hospital: a report of 14720 cardiac arrests from the National Registry of Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Resuscitation</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>58</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>3</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2003</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>297</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>308</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib16"><ce:label>16</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>K.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Ballew</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Philbrick</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Causes of variation in reported in-hospital CPR survival: a critical review</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Resuscitation</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>30</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:date>1995</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>203</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>215</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib17"><ce:label>17</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Buist</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>S.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Bernard</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>T.V.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Nguyen</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Association between clinically abnormal observations and subsequent in-hospital mortality: a prospective study</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Resuscitation</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>62</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>2</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2004</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>137</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>141</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib18"><ce:label>18</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>V.M.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Nadkarni</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>G.L.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Larkin</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.A.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Peberdy</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>First documented rhythm and clinical outcome from in-hospital cardiac arrest among children and adults</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>JAMA</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>295</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>1</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2006</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>50</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>57</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib19"><ce:label>19</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>K.D.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Young</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.S.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Seidel</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Pediatric cardiopulmonary resuscitation: a collective review</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Ann Emerg Med</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>33</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>2</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>1999</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>195</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>205</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib20"><ce:label>20</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.D.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Berg</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>V.M.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Nadkarni</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Zuercher</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>In-hospital pediatric cardiac arrest</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Pediatr Clin North Am</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>55</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>3</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2008</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>589</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>604</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host><sb:comment>x</sb:comment></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib21"><ce:label>21</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>C.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Franklin</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Mathew</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Developing strategies to prevent inhospital cardiac arrest: analyzing responses of physicians and nurses in the hours before the event</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Crit Care Med</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>22</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>2</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>1994</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>244</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>247</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib22"><ce:label>22</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>T.J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Hodgetts</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>G.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Kenward</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>I.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Vlackonikolis</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Incidence, location and reasons for avoidable in-hospital cardiac arrest in a district general hospital</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Resuscitation</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>54</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>2</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2002</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>115</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>123</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib23"><ce:label>23</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>K.M.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Hillman</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>P.J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Bristow</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>T.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Chey</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Duration of life-threatening antecedents prior to intensive care admission</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Intensive Care Med</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>28</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>11</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2002</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>1629</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>1634</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib24"><ce:label>24</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Kause</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>G.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Smith</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>D.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Prytherch</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>A comparison of antecedents to cardiac arrests, deaths and emergency intensive care admissions in Australia and New Zealand, and the United Kingdom&ndash;the ACADEMIA study antecedents to hospital deaths clinical antecedents to in-hospital cardiopulmonary arrest</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Resuscitation</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>62</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>3</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2004</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>275</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>282</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib25"><ce:label>25</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Nurmi</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>V.P.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Harjola</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Nolan</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Observations and warning signs prior to cardiac arrest. Should a medical emergency team intervene earlier?</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Acta Anaesthesiol Scand</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>49</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>5</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2005</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>702</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>706</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib26"><ce:label>26</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Barbetti</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>G.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Lee</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Medical emergency team: a review of the literature</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Nurs Crit Care</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>13</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>2</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2008</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>80</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>85</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib27"><ce:label>27</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>K.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Hillman</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Chen</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Cretikos</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Introduction of the medical emergency team (MET) system: a cluster-randomised controlled trial</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Lancet</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>365</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>9477</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2005</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>2091</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>2097</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib28"><ce:label>28</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Tibballs</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>S.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Kinney</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>T.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Duke</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Reduction of paediatric in-patient cardiac arrest and death with a medical emergency team: preliminary results</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Arch Dis Child</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>90</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>11</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2005</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>1148</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>1152</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib29"><ce:label>29</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>R.J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Brilli</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>R.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Gibson</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.W.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Luria</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Implementation of a medical emergency team in a large pediatric teaching hospital prevents respiratory and cardiopulmonary arrests outside the intensive care unit</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Pediatr Crit Care Med</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>8</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>3</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2007</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>236</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>246</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host><sb:comment>[quiz: 247]</sb:comment></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib30"><ce:label>30</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>E.A.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Hunt</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>K.P.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Zimmer</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.L.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Rinke</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Transition from a traditional code team to a medical emergency team and categorization of cardiopulmonary arrests in a children&apos;s center</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>162</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>2</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2008</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>117</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>122</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib31"><ce:label>31</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>P.J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Sharek</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>L.M.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Parast</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>K.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Leong</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Effect of a rapid response team on hospital-wide mortality and code rates outside the ICU in a children&apos;s hospital</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>JAMA</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>298</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>19</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2007</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>2267</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>2274</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib32"><ce:label>32</ce:label><ce:other-ref><ce:textref>Hanson C, Randolph GD, Erickson J, et&nbsp;al. A reduction in cardiac arrests and duration of clinical instability after implementation of a pediatric rapid response system. Qual Saf Health Care, in press.</ce:textref></ce:other-ref></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib33"><ce:label>33</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.A.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Peberdy</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Cretikos</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>B.S.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Abella</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Recommended guidelines for monitoring, reporting, and conducting research on medical emergency team, outreach, and rapid response systems: an Utstein-style scientific statement: a scientific statement from the International Liaison Committee on Resuscitation (American Heart Association, Australian Resuscitation Council, European Resuscitation Council, Heart and Stroke Foundation of Canada, InterAmerican Heart Foundation, Resuscitation Council of Southern Africa, and the New Zealand Resuscitation Council); the American Heart Association Emergency Cardiovascular Care Committee; the Council on Cardiopulmonary, Perioperative, and Critical Care; and the Interdisciplinary Working Group on Quality of Care and Outcomes Research</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Circulation</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>116</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>21</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2007</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>2481</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>2500</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib34"><ce:label>34</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.A.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Devita</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>R.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Bellomo</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>K.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Hillman</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Findings of the first consensus conference on medical emergency teams</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Crit Care Med</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>34</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>9</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2006</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>2463</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>2478</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib35"><ce:label>35</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>P.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Calzavacca</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>E.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Licari</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>A.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Tee</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>A prospective study of factors influencing the outcome of patients after a Medical Emergency Team review</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Intensive Care Med</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>34</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>11</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2008</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>2112</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>2116</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib36"><ce:label>36</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Patient safety alert. Initiative gives families access to rapid response team</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Healthcare Benchmarks Qual Improv</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>15</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>1 Suppl</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2008</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>1</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>2</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib37"><ce:label>37</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>B.S.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Dean</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Decker</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>D.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Hupp</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Condition HELP: a pediatric rapid response team triggered by patients and parents</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>J Healthc Qual</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>30</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>3</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2008</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>28</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>31</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib38"><ce:label>38</ce:label><ce:other-ref><ce:textref>The Joint Commission. 2009 National Patient Safety Goals.</ce:textref></ce:other-ref></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib39"><ce:label>39</ce:label><ce:other-ref><ce:textref>FAQ. 2008; 2008 August, 21.</ce:textref></ce:other-ref></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib40"><ce:label>40</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>N.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Santiano</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>L.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Young</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>K.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Hillman</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Analysis of Medical Emergency Team calls comparing subjective to &ldquo;objective&rdquo; call criteria</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Resuscitation</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>80</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>1</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2009</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>44</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>49</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib41"><ce:label>41</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Chen</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>A.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Flabouris</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>R.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Bellomo</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>The Medical Emergency Team System and not-for-resuscitation orders: results from the MERIT study</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Resuscitation</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>79</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>3</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2008</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>391</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>397</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib42"><ce:label>42</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>J.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Chen</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>K.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Hillman</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>R.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Bellomo</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>The impact of introducing medical emergency team system on the documentations of vital signs</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Resuscitation</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>80</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>1</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2009</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>35</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>43</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib43"><ce:label>43</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>T.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Jacques</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>G.A.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Harrison</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.L.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>McLaws</ce:surname></sb:author></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Attitudes towards and evaluation of medical emergency teams: a survey of trainees in intensive care medicine</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Anaesth Intensive Care</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>36</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>1</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2008</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>90</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>95</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib44"><ce:label>44</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>R.S.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Braithwaite</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>M.A.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>DeVita</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>R.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Mahidhara</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Use of medical emergency team (MET) responses to detect medical errors</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Qual Saf Health Care</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>13</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>4</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2004</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>255</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>259</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference><ce:bib-reference id="bib45"><ce:label>45</ce:label><sb:reference><sb:contribution><sb:authors><sb:author><ce:given-name>B.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Sarani</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>S.R.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Brenner</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:author><ce:given-name>B.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Gabel</ce:surname></sb:author><sb:et-al/></sb:authors><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Improving sepsis care through systems change: the impact of a medical emergency team</sb:maintitle></sb:title></sb:contribution><sb:host><sb:issue><sb:series><sb:title><sb:maintitle>Jt Comm J Qual Patient Saf</sb:maintitle></sb:title><sb:volume-nr>34</sb:volume-nr></sb:series><sb:issue-nr>3</sb:issue-nr><sb:date>2008</sb:date></sb:issue><sb:pages><sb:first-page>179</sb:first-page><sb:last-page>182</sb:last-page></sb:pages></sb:host><sb:comment>125</sb:comment></sb:reference></ce:bib-reference></ce:bibliography-sec></ce:bibliography></tail></article>