<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.1.0//EN//XML" "art510.dtd" []><exam docsubtype="exm"><item-info><jid>PCL</jid><aid>739</aid><ce:pii>S0031-3955(10)00088-X</ce:pii><ce:doi>10.1016/j.pcl.2010.04.001</ce:doi><ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2010">Elsevier Inc.</ce:copyright></item-info><simple-head><ce:title>CME Accreditation Page and Author Disclosure</ce:title></simple-head><body><ce:exam-answers><ce:section id="sec1"><ce:section-title>Goal Statement</ce:section-title><ce:para>The goal of <ce:italic>Pediatric Clinics of North America</ce:italic> is to keep practicing physicians up to date with current clinical practice in pediatrics by providing timely articles reviewing the state of the art in patient care.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec2"><ce:section-title>Accreditation</ce:section-title><ce:para>The <ce:italic>Pediatric Clinics of North America</ce:italic> is planned and implemented in accordance with the Essential Areas and Policies of the Accreditation Council for Continuing Medical Education (ACCME) through the joint sponsorship of the University Of Virginia School Of Medicine and Elsevier. The University Of Virginia School of Medicine is accredited by the ACCME to provide continuing medical education for physicians.</ce:para><ce:para>The University of Virginia School of Medicine designates this educational activity for a maximum of 15 <ce:italic>AMA PRA Category 1 Credits&trade;</ce:italic> for each issue, 90 credits per year. Physicians should only claim credit commensurate with the extent of their participation in the activity.</ce:para><ce:para>The American Medical Association has determined that physicians not licensed in the US who participate in this CME activity are eligible for a maximum of 15 <ce:italic>AMA PRA Category 1 Credits&trade;</ce:italic> for each issue, 90 credits per year.</ce:para><ce:para>Credit can be earned by reading the text material, taking the CME examination online at <ce:inter-ref xlink:href="http://www.theclinics.com/home/cme">http://www.theclinics.com/home/cme</ce:inter-ref>, and completing the evaluation. After taking the test, you will be required to review any and all incorrect answers. Following completion of the test and evaluation, your credit will be awarded and you may print your certificate.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec3"><ce:section-title>Faculty Disclosure/Conflict of Interest</ce:section-title><ce:para>The University of Virginia School of Medicine, as an ACCME accredited provider, endorses and strives to comply with the Accreditation Council for Continuing Medical Education (ACCME) Standards of Commercial Support, Commonwealth of Virginia statutes, University of Virginia policies and procedures, and associated federal and private regulations and guidelines on the need for disclosure and monitoring of proprietary and financial interests that may affect the scientific integrity and balance of content delivered in continuing medical education activities under our auspices.</ce:para><ce:para>The University of Virginia School of Medicine requires that all CME activities accredited through this institution be developed independently and be scientifically rigorous, balanced and objective in the presentation/discussion of its content, theories and practices.</ce:para><ce:para>All authors/editors participating in an accredited CME activity are expected to disclose to the readers relevant financial relationships with commercial entities occurring within the past 12 months (such as grants or research support, employee, consultant, stock holder, member of speakers bureau, etc.). The University of Virginia School of Medicine will employ appropriate mechanisms to resolve potential conflicts of interest to maintain the standards of fair and balanced education to the reader. Questions about specific strategies can be directed to the Office of Continuing Medical Education, University of Virginia School of Medicine, Charlottesville, Virginia.</ce:para><ce:para>The faculty and staff of the University of Virginia Office of Continuing Medical Education have no financial affiliations to disclose.</ce:para><ce:para><ce:bold>The authors/editors listed below have identified no financial or professional relationships for themselves or their spouse/partner:</ce:bold></ce:para><ce:para>David Angert, BS; Magdalena Bartoszewska, BA; Delmas J. Bolin, MD, PhD; Christopher C. Cheatham, PhD; Eugene Diokno, MD; Martin B. Draznin, MD; Donald E. Greydanus, MD (Guest Editor); Carla Holloway (Acquisitions Editor); Trudy A. McKanna, MS; Michael G. Miller, EdD, ATC, CSCS; Hatim Omar, MD; Dilip R. Patel, MD, FSAM; Neil D. Patel; Helen D. Pratt, PhD; Vinay Reddy, MD; Karen Rheuban, MD (Test Author); Dale Rowe, MD; Eric A. Schaff, MD; Saad Siddiqui, MD; and Helga V. Toriello, PhD.</ce:para><ce:para><ce:bold>The authors/editors listed below identified the following professional or financial affiliations for themselves or their spouse/partner:</ce:bold></ce:para><ce:para><ce:bold>Cnythia L. Feucht, PharmD, BCPS'</ce:bold>s spouse serves on the Speakers Bureau for Wyeth.</ce:para><ce:para><ce:bold>Manmohan Kamboj, MD</ce:bold> serves on the speakers bureau for Pfizer.</ce:para><ce:para><ce:bold>Disclosure of Discussion of Non-FDA Approved Uses for Pharmaceutical Products and/or Medical Devices</ce:bold></ce:para><ce:para>The University of Virginia School of Medicine, as an ACCME provider, requires that all faculty presenters identify and disclose any off-label uses for pharmaceutical and medical device products. The University of Virginia School of Medicine recommends that each physician fully review all the available data on new products or procedures prior to clinical use.</ce:para></ce:section><ce:section id="sec4"><ce:section-title>To Enroll</ce:section-title><ce:para>To enroll in the Pediatric Clinics of North America Continuing Medical Education program, call customer service at 1-800-654-2452 or visit us online at <ce:inter-ref xlink:href="http://www.theclinics.com/home/cme">www.theclinics.com/home/cme</ce:inter-ref>. The CME program is available to subscribers for an additional fee of $223.00</ce:para></ce:section></ce:exam-answers></body></article>