<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE simple-article PUBLIC "-//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.1.0//EN//XML" "art510.dtd" [<!ENTITY fx1 SYSTEM "fx1" NDATA IMAGE><!ENTITY fx2 SYSTEM "fx2" NDATA IMAGE>]><simple-article docsubtype="edi"><item-info><jid>PCL</jid><aid>737</aid><ce:pii>S0031-3955(10)00072-6</ce:pii><ce:doi>10.1016/j.pcl.2010.03.007</ce:doi><ce:copyright type="full-transfer" year="2010">Elsevier Inc.</ce:copyright></item-info><simple-head><ce:title>Preface: Adolescents and Sports</ce:title><ce:author-group><ce:author id="au1"><ce:given-name>Dilip R.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Patel</ce:surname><ce:degrees>MD, FSAM</ce:degrees><ce:e-address type="email">patel@kcms.msu.edu</ce:e-address></ce:author></ce:author-group><ce:author-group><ce:author id="au2"><ce:given-name>Donald E.</ce:given-name><ce:surname>Greydanus</ce:surname><ce:degrees>MD, FSAM, FIAP (H)</ce:degrees><ce:e-address type="email">greydanus@kcms.msu.edu</ce:e-address></ce:author><ce:affiliation><ce:textfn>Department of Pediatrics and Human Development, Michigan State University College of Human Medicine, MSU/Kalamazoo Center for Medical Studies, 1000 Oakland Drive, Kalamazoo, MI 49008-1284, USA</ce:textfn></ce:affiliation></ce:author-group></simple-head><body><ce:sections><ce:para><ce:display><ce:figure><ce:caption><ce:simple-para>Dilip R. Patel, MD, FSAM <ce:italic>Guest Editor</ce:italic></ce:simple-para></ce:caption><ce:link locator="fx1"/></ce:figure></ce:display><ce:display><ce:figure><ce:caption><ce:simple-para>Donald E. Greydanus, MD, FSAM, FIAP (H) <ce:italic>Guest Editor</ce:italic></ce:simple-para></ce:caption><ce:link locator="fx2"/></ce:figure></ce:display></ce:para><ce:para>Dr Nathan J. Smith was the guest editor for the December 1982 issue of <ce:italic>Pediatric Clinics of North America</ce:italic> devoted to sports medicine. This was followed by publication of an issue of <ce:italic>Pediatric Clinics of North America</ce:italic> devoted to sports medicine in October 1990, coedited by Dr Albert Hergenroeder and Dr James Garrick, and in August and October 2002 issues edited by Dr Eugene F. Luckstead Sr. It has been a humbling experience for us to follow such giants in the field. We consider it a great privilege and honor to be guest editors of this issue of <ce:italic>Pediatric Clinics of North America</ce:italic> devoted to the adolescent athlete. Our goal is to provide reviews of selected topics of relevance to pediatricians and other primary care physicians in their daily practice.</ce:para><ce:para>We thank all the authors for sacrificing their time and sharing their expertise to contribute articles to this issue. We thank Carla Holloway, editor, for her guidance and patience during this project from start to finish. Dilip Patel especially appreciates continued professional guidance and support from Dr Hergenroeder.</ce:para><ce:para>On a personal level, we would like to especially note that we have enjoyed our years of friendship with Dr Luckstead (Gene)&mdash;thank you Gene for years of wisdom, friendship, and collegiality&mdash;looking forward to many more years of the same.</ce:para></ce:sections></body></simple-article>